{
  "reference_number": "78",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Target needs to be achievable and not a pie in the sky ideal"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Asking for net zero CO2 would destroy many industries that rely on CO2 production such as fertiliser and industrial processes. Goals\n need to be set with this in mind or New Zealand will have no productive industrial base."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Overseas cabin reduction doesn't work. Carbon trading and similar systems do nothing to promote industries taking proactive\n choices in reducing emissions, they simply buy away their errors. Systems need to promote proactive choices in industry to reduce\n\n or mitigate emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The goal is long term sustainability. To have it be revised in a transient political climate is stupidity."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Are these plans flexible to change or review within the 15 year window? Without more detail it is difficult to make a decision."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "The point of goals is stewardship, sustainability, responsibility and long term planning. If it is planned correctly why would we risk\n\n compromising those principles and goals for transient political pandering. We need to ensure that the changes being made do not\n compromise the overall goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Needs to be a greater and clearer set of considerations."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Putting off climate change is the current global issue. the more we put it off the greater the problem becomes and the harder to fix."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "New Zealand is a primary industry driven economy. We must reconsider and also give effect to this basic fact. We rely on emissions for\nour economic process. To change the economic process is to change the pressure on the environment. Setting goals and\n\nobjectives does not provide leadership forward creating an economy that can function without emissions. This needs to be another\ngoal to work towards and consider since if our economy relies on emissions we will never truly reach the goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "International emissions have nothing to do with us. We should set an example and not be swayed by the inactivity of the international\n\ncommunity."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Emissions trading is almost entirely pointless. We don't want to have profitable but unethical business do nothing to twice their\n\nemissions. There needs to be a mechanism for so all business to consider how they can reduce their own emissions and not just\noffload the problem to someone else."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Need to ensure that the commission isn't appointed by government but is independent as it could fall prey to partisan political\n\npressure."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes especially in the planning space to give guidance on how to respond or restrict activities in increasingly strong weather patterns."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I doubt many organisations would know or care enough to join. Especially small businesses run by individuals. but it's a nice idea."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The climate change goals need to understand the underlying reason for pressure on the environment. We have an event based on\n\nprimary production. On concert with this bill needs to be national leadership on changing our economy to one that does not require\npotentially polluting industry."
    }
  ]
}
